So when we think about where to focus our problem-solving efforts,
one of the techniques we like to use is something called the 80/20 approach.
It's sometimes called the Pareto principle.
And the idea behind this is that you usually get 80% of the benefits or insights
by doing 20% of the work.
So when you think about applying the 80/20, it applies both in short-term
problem-solving time horizons, as well as long-term time horizons.
In the short term, it's important to do because there's a very finite time
you have to solve a problem.
And so you want to think about: what are those 20% of the analyses you may reasonably be able
to get done — let's say in one week — in order to get the best answer you can in that time?
In a longer time horizon — over a series of weeks, over a series of months —
it's still important to think about applying the 80/20 principle,
so not boiling the ocean — but in this case, it's particularly important
to iterate on that prioritisation approach.
And so as you're going through the analyses,
as new insights are being developed, you want to think about
how that might change how I'm prioritising my time.
So for example, if one of the analyses you conduct surprises you and eliminates
one of the branches from your tree, because you've disproved that hypothesis —
well, now you know you no longer need to do a series of analyses
that may have followed from there,
and you can prioritise your problem-solving time appropriately.
So what does applying the 80/20 principle look like in practice?
Let me give you an example.
So I was once valuing a business,
and this business had well over 200 different lines of business.
And what we needed to do was figure out, in the amount of time that we had,
how to come up with an appropriate valuation. Now, if we'd tried to go
and value each business one by one, through all 200,
we never would have had enough time to get to the right answer.
And so what we needed to think about was: how do we apply the 80/20 principle?
And in this case, there were about 30 businesses
which were going to have a disproportionate impact on the valuation. So we really focused
on valuing those businesses, to get us to the solution we needed
to address the problem we were trying to solve.
And that's an example where 80/20 is a guidance. It doesn't literally mean
you only get to do 20% of the analysis,
but it's meant to prompt you to think about what the things are that you can and should
look at, that are going to get you to the answer most quickly.
So when you're applying the 80/20 principle in the real world,
there are a couple of things that are important to keep in mind.
One is being comfortable with ambiguity and uncertainty.
You're getting, like, 80% of the way there to the answer — not 100%.
And at some point you need to be comfortable with that.
And the key is to ask yourself: do you feel, directionally, you've gotten
a sufficient level of detail to move forward?
And this can vary by context. So if you're thinking about sizing a new market
and you're trying to understand: is it a
10-million-dollar opportunity or a 100-million opportunity —
there's probably a lower level of precision you need to get to.
But if you're working at a semiconductor manufacturing plant and you look at the error rates,
you might actually need two or three or more decimal places of precision.
And so think about: at what point are you comfortable enough to move on?
Because explicitly, you're not going to be able to get 100% of the way there.